Finding Aid for Burrows family papers, 1760-1916
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Burrows family papers 1760-1916
Burrows family
(in 7 boxes)
6 linear feet
85895 Aa 2
Burrows-Avery-Smith families of New York, Connecticut, and Michigan. Correspondence and business papers of Lorenzo Burrows, New York Congressman, 1849-1853; George L. Burrows, Saginaw, Michigan, banker and speculator; material concerning the Whig Party and New York state politics, 1848-1860. Correspondents include: Millard Fillmore, Washington Hunt, and John Young.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Herbert G. Watkins (donor no. 2482 ) and came to the library in 1947.
The collection is open to research.
The Burrows family was a prominent Connecticut, New York, and Michigan business family. The papers begin in the mid-eighteenth century with Latham Avery, a Connecticut businessman. His daughter Jerusha married Roswell Burrows, another prosperous businessman. Among their children were Lorenzo Burrows, Roswell Burrows Jr., and Latham Burrows. Lorenzo Burrows, who served in Congress, had three children: George L. Burrows, Emeline Burrows, and Lorenzo Burrows, Jr. Among the children of the younger Roswell Burrows was Mary E. Burrows who married Alexander Stewart. Their child was Julia Ann Stewart (later Mrs. Julia Smith).
Lorenzo Burrows was born March 15, 1805 in Groton, Connecticut. He attended academies in Plainfield, Conn., and Westerly, Rhode Island, then in 1824, he moved to New York, settling in Albion, Orleans County, where he assisted his brother Roswell S. Burrows in his mercantile pursuits. He became a businessman himself, eventually helping his brother to establish the Bank of Orleans in 1839, also serving as its cashier. Burrows was politically active, serving two terms as a Whig in the US House of Representatives (1849-1853). He subsequently served as comptroller of the State of New York (1855-1857), director and president of the Niagara Falls International Bridge Company, regent of the University of New York (1858-1885) and commissioner of the Mount Albion Cemetery (1862-1885). He died March 6, 1885.
George L. Burrows, Lorenzo's son, was a Saginaw banker, heading the firm of G. L. Burrows & Co., as well as being member of the firms of Burrows & Eaton, and Burrows & Rust. Burrows was the owner of large tracts of pine and farming lands.
The Burrows / Avery / Smith collection was brought together and preserved by Emeline Burrows (daughter of Lorenzo Burrows) and Julia Smith (granddaughter of the elder Roswell Burrows).
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence and other papers of family members (arranged chronologically); Family records; Topical files; Visual Materials; and Financial materials.
Subjects:
American Party.; Avery family.; Banks and banking--Michigan--Saginaw.; Connecticut.; Democratic National Convention (1880: Cincinnati, Ohio); Democratic Party (U.S.); Elections--New York (State)--1848.; Elections--New York (State)--1852.; Elections--New York (State)--1858.; Elections--New York (State)--1880.; Forest fires--Michigan--Thumb District.; Free Soil Party (U.S.); Huron County (Mich.); Equal Rights Party (N.Y.); Nativism.; New York (State); New York (State)--Politics and government--1775-1865.; New York (State)--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Saginaw (Mich.); Sanilac County (Mich.); Tilden, Samuel Jones, 1814-1866.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1848.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1852.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1858.; United States--Politics and government--1845-1861.; United States--Politics and government--1877-1881.; Whig Party (U.S.); World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Burrows, Emmeline.; Burrows, George Lord, b. 1836.; Burrows, Lorenzo, 1805-1885.; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874.; Hunt, Washington, 1811-1867.; Young, John, 1802-1852.
- Correspondence and other papers of family members
  The bulk of the collection has been arranged into a chronological series: Correspondence and other papers of family members. This series dates from 1761 to 1916 and contains an amalgam of personal, business, and political materials. As these papers were accumulated by different family members, it was not always possible to separate papers into series by name of either Burrows, Avery, or Smith family member. To facilitate access, therefore, the papers were arranged into one chronological sequence.
  The earliest materials in this series were of Latham Avery, a Connecticut businessman. This is followed by papers of his daughter, her husband Roswell Burrows, and two of their children Roswell Burrows Jr. and Lorenzo Burrows. Papers from the period when Lorenzo Burrows was served in Congress consist primarily of letters to him requesting his aid in obtaining positions within the government and letters about his Whig party activities. It is in the papers for the years 1849 to 1853, that the researcher will find correspondence from Whig politicians, Washington Hunt and Millard Fillmore.
  For the mid to late nineteenth century, the correspondence is primarily to Julia Smith from her sister and her nieces about family matters. For the twentieth century, the letters are mainly addressed to Emeline Burrows and also relate to family matters. Business correspondence is interspersed throughout with the family letters.
  - Undated 1761-1829 (Box 1)
    (Latham Avery papers; also Burrows family)
    - Undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1761-1799 include farm inventories (Box 1)
    - 1800-1809 include letter, November 28, 1808 describing the Napoleonic Wars (Box 1)
    - 1810-1815 (Box 1)
    - 1816-1819 (Box 1)
    - 1820-1829 (Box 1)
  - 1830-1847
    (letters of Julia and Alexander Smith; also Burrows family)
    - 1830-1835 (Box 1)
    - 1836-1837 (Box 1)
    - 1838 (Box 1)
      (include material concerning the American Republican Party)
    - 1839 (Box 1)
    - 1840-1842 (Box 1)
    - 1843-1844 (Box 1)
    - 1845-1846 include letter from Washington Hunt, October 9, 1846 (Box 1)
    - 1847 (Box 1)
  - 1848-1852
    (Congressional papers of Lorenzo Burrows and other family correspondence)
    - 1848 include letter from Washington Hunt, October 13, 1848 (Box 1)
    - 1849 include correspondence from Millard Fillmore, July 24, 1849, December 4, 1849 several letters from Washington Hunt; and letters concerning the Loco-Foco Party or the Equal Rights Party of New York, November 29, 1849, December 18, 1849, December 19, 1849 (Box 1)
    - 1850 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1851 include letters of Whig politician John Young, January 6, 1851, January 23, 1851 also letter concerning the Free Soil Party, February 6, 1851 (Box 1)
    - May-December 1851; include letter December 1851 from Washington Hunt (Box 1)
    - January-March 1852 (Box 1)
      (include letter concerning election of 1852 with correspondence March 16, 1852 concerning Daniel Webster's aspirations for the presidential nomination)
    - April-June 1852 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1852 (Box 1)
  - 1853-1860
    (various family members represented)
    - 1853-1854 (Box 1)
    - 1855 include letter of Millard Fillmore (Box 1)
    - 1856-1857 (Box 1)
    - 1858 (Box 1)
      (Lorenzo Burrows political activities)
    - 1859-1860 (Box 1)
  - 1861-1885
    (mainly letters from family members addressed to Julia Smith; also Lorenzo Burrows business papers)
    - 1861 (Box 2)
    - 1862 include letters from George L. Burrows giving his impressions of Saginaw, Michigan, July 22, 1862, September 8, 1862 (Box 2)
    - 1863 (Box 2)
    - 1864 include list of offices held by Lorenzo Burrows (Box 2)
    - 1865 (Box 2)
    - 1866-1870 include material on the Niagara Falls Suspension Bridge Company, 1869 (Box 2)
    - 1871-1872 (Box 2)
    - 1873 (Box 2)
    - 1874-1875 (Box 2)
    - 1875 (Box 2)
    - 1876 (Box 2)
    - 1877 (Box 2)
    - 1878 (Box 2)
    - 1879 (Box 2)
    - 1880 (Box 2)
      (include material concerning the Democratic National Convention at Cincinnati with comments about Samuel Tilden, June 17, 1880 and May 27, 1880)
    - 1881 (Box 2)
      (include material concerning forest fire in Huron and Sanilac counties, September 22, 1881)
    - 1882 (Box 2)
    - 1883 (Box 2)
    - 1884-1885 (Box 2)
  - 1886-1916
    (mainly letters to Emeline Burrows from brother George Burrows and other family members; also letters to Julia Smith until her death)
    - 1886 (Box 2)
    - 1887 (Box 2)
    - 1888 (Box 2)
    - 1889 (Box 2)
    - 1890-1891 (Box 3)
    - 1892-1893 (Box 3)
    - 1894-1895 (Box 3)
    - 1896-1897 (Box 3)
    - 1898-1899 (Box 3)
    - 1900-1903 (Box 3)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 3)
    - 1906-1907 (Box 3)
    - 1908 (Box 3)
    - January-June 1909 (Box 3)
    - July-December 1909 (Box 3)
    - January-June 1910 (Box 3)
    - July-December 1910 (Box 3)
    - January-June 1911 (Box 3)
    - July-December 1911 (Box 3)
    - 1912 (Box 3)
    - 1913 (Box 3)
    - January-June 1914 (Box 3)
    - July-December 1914 (Box 3)
    - January-March 1915 (Box 3)
    - April-June 1915 (Box 3)
    - July-September 1915 (Box 3)
    - October-December 1915 (Box 3)
      (include letter concerning English attitudes toward World War I, December 20, 1915)
    - 1916 (Box 3)
- Family records
  - Roswell Burrows
    - Roswell Burrows letter book 1835-1837 (Box 4)
    - Estate of Roswell Burrows (Box 4)
    - Roswell Burrows speech 1860 (reprint) (Box 4)
    - Dr. Roswell Burrows church meeting book 1835-1836 (Box 4)
    - Roswell Burrows account with New London Bank (Box 4)
  - Lorenzo Burrows
    - Lorenzo Burrows algebra problem book (Box 4)
    - Lorenzo Burrows cash books 1838-1849 (Box 4)
    - Lorenzo Burrows abstract of census (Box 4)
    - Lorenzo Burrows misc. (Box 4)
    - Newspapers containing articles primarily about Lorenzo Burrows 1839-1881 (Box 4)
      (in box 7)
  - Lucy L. Burrows
    - Sketchbook (Box 4)
  - Emeline Burrows
    - Household account book of Emeline Burrows 1916 (Box 4)
  - Smith family
    - A.E. Smith letter book 1840 (Box 4)
    - Inventory of the property of Julia A. Smith (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook of general interest 1850s (Box 4)
      (the volume was formerly used to draft Smith related business correspondence, 1831-1832)
    - Scrapbook of general interest 1850s (Box 4)
      (volume was formerly business ledger, 1804-1812 perhaps of Smith family member)
  - Avery Family
    - Latham Avery estate (Box 4)
    - Composition book (Latham Avery ?) (Box 4)
  - Elizabeth Stewart and family (copies of letters) 1886 (Box 4)
- Topical files
  - Albion Historical Club (Box 4)
  - Church activities clippings (Box 4)
  - Cooking and medical recipes (Box 4)
  - Family genealogy (Box 4)
  - First Baptist Church (Albion, NY) (Box 4)
  - First National Bank of Albion. Clippings concerning the scandal surrounding the First National Bank of Albion 1884 (Box 4)
  - Historical Conversation Club (Box 4)
  - Niagara Falls International Bridge Co. (Box 4)
  - Poetry book (Box 5)
  - Printed material 1801-1910, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Sermon. Book containing transcription of sermon preached by W. H. Sloan June 24, 1883 (Box 5)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Postcards (Box 5)
  - Greeting cards (Box 5)
- Financial materials
  - Account book 1852-1853 (Box 5)
  - Pocket account books, receipt books (Box 5)
  - Vouchers (Box 6)
  - Receipts (Box 6)
  - Contracts (Box 6)
  - Insurance policies (Box 6)
  - Farmers' Bank of Orleans record books 1838-1860, 3 volumes (Box 7)
  - Account of Bank of Orleans with R.S. and L. Burrows (Box 7)
  - Inventory book 1839-1881 (Box 7)
  - Ledger 1836-1862 (Box 7)